Finding Aid for Lynn M. Bartlett papers, 1925-1970
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Lynn M. Bartlett papers 1925-1970, 1955-1969
Bartlett, Lynn M. (Lynn Mahlon), 1904-1970.
1 oversize folder
4 microfilm reels
4 linear feet
85809 Aa 2; UAm
Educational administrator, Michigan Superintendent of Public Instruction, 1957-1965, and official with the Johnson administration. Correspondence, reports, and newspaper clippings concerning his public career, political campaigns for state office, work in the constitutional convention, and interest in educational topics.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was donated by Josephine Bartlett (donor no. 5167 ) and came to the library in several accessions beginning in 1971.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Lynn M. Bartlett was born July 12, 1904 in Portland, New York. He earned his A.B. (1927), M.A. (1930), and Ph.D. (1954) degrees at the University of Michigan. In 1960, Northern Michigan University awarded him the honorary degree of Doctor of Laws.
Bartlett began his career in the field of education as a rural school teacher in Cherry Creek, New York. From 1927 to 1929 he was a psychologist in the Detroit Public Schools. On July 24, 1937 he married the former Josephine Katherine Kriser, an elementary school teacher who shared his interest in education.
Over the period from 1930 to 1957, Bartlett taught briefly in turn at Eastern Michigan University, the University of Michigan, and Wayne State University, while also serving in a series of administrative positions for the Grosse Pointe Public Schools. On July 1, 1957, following his successful election campaign, Bartlett left the post of Assistant Superintendent for Pupil Personnel for the Grosse Pointe Public Schools to assume office as State Superintendent of Public Instruction for Michigan.
Bartlett served as State Superintendent for eight years until July 1, 1965, at which time he became Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for Education in the Johnson Administration, a role that made him the director of the school system responsible for educating the children of armed forces personnel. In June of 1968, he was nominated by President Johnson as Assistant Secretary for Education in the Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. He assumed the post in early July and held it until his death on November 28, 1970.
Bartlett was a member of the National Education Association, American Association of School Administrators, American Psychological Association, the International Council on Exceptional Children, the Michigan Education Association, Michigan Psychological Association, and other organizations.
The Lynn M. Bartlett papers have been arranged into five series. The first three series were accumulated in his capacity as State Superintendent of Public Instruction, Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for Education, and Assistant Secretary for Education within the U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare. The researcher should note that although these series have been designated with the title of the office that Bartlett held, these series do not include the official files from those agencies. Records for the state office will be found in the Michigan State Archives; and records for the two federal positions held either reside within the agency itself or have been transferred to the National Archives. These three series consist of personal materials, such as speeches, personal letters (e.g., letters of congratulation, and thanks yous), and other files not deemed to be part of the agency's files.
The final two series consist of Biographical/Personal and Pre-1957 Activities and papers of his wife, an East Lansing, Michigan school teacher, Josephine K. Bartlett.
Subjects:
Bartlett, Lynn M. (Lynn Mahlon), 1904-1970.; Democratic Party (Mich.); Education--Michigan.; Educational law and legislation--Michigan.; Educational law and legislation--United States.; Elections--Michigan--1957.; Elections--Michigan--1958.; Elections--Michigan--1960.; Elections--Michigan--1961.; Elections--Michigan--1963.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Michigan. Dept. of Public Instruction.; Michigan--Politics and government--1946-1960.; Michigan--Politics and government--1961-1970.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Bartlett, Lynn M. (Lynn Mahlon), 1904-1970.; Banquet halls.; Churches--Michigan--Houghton.; Houghton (Mich.)--Churches.; Michigan School for the Deaf.; St. Ignatius Loyola Church (Houghton, Mich.); Williams, G. Mennen, 1911-1988.
Contributors:
Bartlett, Josephine K.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Michigan Superintendent Of Public Instruction 1957-1965
  The largest series - Michigan Superintendent of Public Instruction (2.0 linear ft.; 1957-1965) - relates more to the politics of the office than it does to the issues faced by the superintendent. At this time, the office was an elective one, and thus much of Bartlett's files relate to his campaigns for office. Types of documents include correspondence, newspaper clippings, and campaign materials. The remainder of the series consists of speeches given by Bartlett and subject files accumulated by the superintendent on such educational issues as federal aid to education.
  - Correspondence 1955-1964, 8 folders (Box 1)
  - Michigan politics 1955-1965, 9 folders (Box 1)
  - LMB campaign for reelection (newspaper clippings) 1961, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - LMB campaign for reelection (newspaper clippings) 1963, 6 folders (Box 1)
  - Speeches 1957-1958, 1960-1961, 1963-1965, 29 folders (Box 2)
  - Topical files
    - Campaign Literature/Political Views 1961-1965 (Box 2)
    - Constitutional Convention 1961-1962 (Box 2)
    - Eastern Michigan University
      - Correspondence/Consultant Report 1962-1963 (Box 2)
      - Newspaper Clippings/Romney caricature 1963 (Box 2)
    - Education in Michigan: 1900-1965 Report, 1967 (Box 2)
    - Elementary and Secondary Education Act of 1965 (Box 2)
      (include Bartlett testimony before congressional committee)
    - Federal aid to education 1961-1962 (Box 2)
    - Romney, George
      - Newspaper clippings relating to Bartlett's refusal to invite Romney to speak before the Citizen's Conference on Education 1963, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Russian trip 1964 (speeches, etc.), 1964-1965 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan newspaper clippings 1960 (Box 2)
    - Wayne State University papers 1955-1964 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (largely concerning educational topics and issues) 1955-1965, 6 folders (Box 2)
- Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense For Education, U.S. Dept. of Defense 1965-1968
  The Deputy Assistant Secretary of Defense for Education series (0.5 linear ft.; 1965-1968) consists of speeches, personal (rather than official) correspondence, and subject files relating to some of Bartlett's activities while in the U.S. Department of Defense.
  - Speeches 1965-1969 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1965-1968, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Topical Files
    - Acceptance of position (press release and sampling of letters of congratulation) (Box 3)
    - Cater, Douglas (Special Assistant to the President) (Box 3)
    - Council of Chief State School Officers 1965-1968 (Box 3)
    - Far East trip 1967 (Box 3)
    - Job description (and other general information) (Box 3)
    - Overseas Dependents Schools (Box 3)
    - Overseas Schools Advisory Council (Box 3)
- Assistant Secretary For Education, U.S. Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare 1968-1970
  The series, Assistant Secretary for Education within the U.S. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare (0.6 linear ft.; 1968-1970) includes speeches, correspondence, and scattered subject files.
  - Speeches (Box 3)
  - Correspondence 1968-1969 mainly letters of congratulation, etc. (Box 3)
  - Correspondence A-Z 1968, 7 folders (Box 3)
    (separate folders for American Association of School Administrators and Michigan State University)
  - Topical files
    - Federal Interagency Committee on Education 1968 (Box 3)
    - Higher education study 1968-1969 (Box 3)
    - Job position (general information (Box 3)
    - Legislation 1968 (Box 4)
    - Presidential election (education issues) 1968 (Box 4)
- Biographical/Personal and Pre-1957 Activities circa 1926-1970
  The fourth series contains materials labeled Biographical/Personal and Pre-1957 Activities (0.4 linear ft.; ca. 1926-1970). The series includes informational clippings, articles written by or about Bartlett, a student paper he wrote while in college, and photographs. There is one subject file relating to his involvement with the Michigan Psychological Association.
  - Biographical information, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Personal correspondence 1957-1965 (Box 4)
  - Photographs, 4 envelopes (in 1 folder) (Box 4)
    (Portraits; photographs of Bartlett as part of various ceremonies and presentations; photographs from Citizens' Conference on Education held in 1958 aerial view of the Michigan School for the Deaf, Flint, Michigan; and interior of St. Ignatius Loyola Church in Houghton, Michigan, ca. 1893)
  - Photographs (Folder UAm)
  - Michigan Psychological Association 1935-1953 (scattered dates) (Box 4)
  - Doctoral thesis, 1 microfilm reel (Reel 1)
  - Public addresses, appearances, and testimonies 1957-1963 (Reel 2)
  - Public addresses, appearances, and testimonies 1957-1963 (Reel 3)
    continued
  - Press releases, 1957-1963, 1 microfilm reel (Reel 4)
- Josephine Kriser Bartlett 1929-1970
  The last series (0.5 linear ft.; 1929-1970) consists of files of Josephine Bartlett, who was a career elementary school teacher in East Lansing, Michigan. This series is valuable for the notes that Bartlett took while a student at the University of Michigan. These notes are for English and history classes.
  - Biographical/personal information (Box 4)
  - Correspondence (miscellaneous) (Box 4)
  - Class notes taken (mainly in English and history classes) while a student at the University of Michigan 1929, 1932, 1935, 7 folders (Box 4)
  - Teacher's files
    - Work plans and log (Box 4)
    - Annual report as a teacher 1938 (Box 4)
  - Sixth grade class, Central School, East Lansing
    - Class on communism vs. democracy 1962 (Box 4)
    - Class on creative writing 1961-1965 (Box 4)
  - Political and community activities (Box 4)
  - Narrative account of trip to Europe 1961 (Box 4)
  - Better Human Relations Committee 1963 (Box 4)